<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Firewall | Kevin Coughlin]]></title>
  <link href="http://kevintcoughlin.com/blog/categories/firewall/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://kevintcoughlin.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-10T00:09:37-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://kevintcoughlin.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kevin Coughlin]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kevintcoughlin@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Android Development Behind a Firewall]]></title>
    <link href="http://kevintcoughlin.com/blog/2013/11/14/android-development-behind-a-firewall/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-14T20:25:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://kevintcoughlin.com/blog/2013/11/14/android-development-behind-a-firewall</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Configure Android Studio to use an HTTP Proxy</h2>

<p>If you&rsquo;ve had problems using Android Studio or the Android SDK Manager behind a Firewall then these two configuration changes may help you configure your development environment. First, configure your Android studio to bypass the firewall by changing its HTTP Proxy settings. To do this navigate to <code>Preferences &gt; HTTP Proxy</code>. You&rsquo;ll be presented with the following dialog:</p>

<p><img src="http://i.imgur.com/btmwNDC.png" alt="Android Studio HTTP Proxy Settings Dialog" /></p>

<p>Configure Android Studio to use your HTTP Proxy by filling in the inputs with the correct settings. Once you&rsquo;re done you can check that the proxy works by pressing the <code>Check Connection</code> button and entering a URL that is typically blocked by your firewall.</p>

<h2>Configure the Android SDK Manager to use an HTTP Proxy</h2>

<p>If your Android SDK Manager is unable to make HTTP calls while installing / updating then you can edit its configuration file to use an HTTP Proxy. To do this you&rsquo;ll need to edit its config file named <code>androidtools.cgf</code>. If you are on a UNIX machine you can typically find it at the following path: <code>~/.android/androidtool.cfg</code>. Once you open the config file in an editor, append / modify the http proxy and http port settings like the following:</p>

<pre><code>sdkman.force.http=true
http.proxyPort=[PORT NUMBER]
http.proxyHost=[IP ADDRESS]
</code></pre>

<p>Where <code>[PORT NUMBER]</code> and <code>[IP ADDRESS]</code> are the correct settings for your HTTP proxy and the first line forces the manager to use HTTP. Save your modifications to the configuration file and you should then be able to fetch and install SDK assets behind your firewall.</p>

<p>Hope those two tips help you configure your Android development environment behind a firewall!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
